Okay, greetings.
So, this is
cohort 8 in the discussion on chapter 9
and 10.
They're good chapters. They bring
together a lot of questions. 10 is of
course an overview and looking out in
the end of the book and nine deals with
a lot of experimental topics.
So, does anyone want to start with a
section or a quote or a question from
what they've been working on in the time
between or anything pre-existing in the
document or anywhere to start?
It could be on
nine or 10
or as 10 sort of deals with everything.
It could kind of be any any any
topic that anyone wants to bring up.
existing section that someone
highlighted or a question they wrote
down or or we can just go through nine
and 10.
Okay, just raise your hand in in Zoom or
write in the chat if you have a specific
thought or if you want to go somewhere
else.
So nine is going to flip the direction
that the generative models are being
deployed in relative to the rest of the
book. In the chapters leading up to nine
pretty much ad hoc or aboninio the from
starting position a generative model is
specified and then it's used to generate
synthetic outcomes. Nine is going to
flip that by saying okay what if we
already have empirical data but we want
to recover or infer parameters that are
unobserved from empirical data. That's
what this chapter is all about. going
from having a generative model of a
situation kind of like a music box like
you built it, you run the crank and it
puts out music. Well, now there's a
situation where you have a recording of
bird song or mouse behavior or whatever
it is and you want to go back to recover
the structure or the parameters of a
generative model. So this is a more
empirically grounded. This is the kind
of stuff in the figures that you'll see
like in a paper Michael or Okay.
just anyone can unmute if they want to
ask a question.
Um,
and and as always with this group of
authors in the book, there's just so
many fun standalone spicy quotations
that that can be discussed even with any
background.
9.2 two goes into a very important
structural perspective on cognitive
modeling on behavioral modeling and it's
represented in this figure 9.1. So now
we're looking at that kind of figure 4.3
figure 7.3 discreet time generative
model. So that that figure would have
looked just
like that. But now we're saying okay so
that's the artifact that we're making is
the pom dp that has this graphical
structure but let's think about our
laboratory as well. What we're calling
observations for the mouse or for the
agent who we're modeling are under the
control of the laboratory apparatus and
then what we're calling actions or
outputs of the agent that we're studying
are actually observations for us as
researchers. And there are parameters of
our laboratory that set up the context
for the situation. So it's a good
reminder that just because something is
called like O or observation, it doesn't
mean that it is simply only an
observation. It's that's a perspective
on the direction that that data point is
used for. And here's kind of zooming out
to the um the bird in the laboratory and
a reminder that once an observation for
the system of interest could be under
the control of the experimentter and
that is going to come into play because
now we're thinking about like from the
research lab or behavioral studies
how do we talk about that generative
model. Okay. Um there's two reasons for
fitting a computational model to observe
behavior or you can come up with more
lump or split however you see fit. This
is what they're going to focus on. This
is the rationale for chapter 9. The
first is to estimate parameters of
interest from that model that best
explain the behavior of specific subject
or group of subjects.
So simple example, if we're going to
flip a coin, we're going to get this
series of heads and tails, but there's
this unobserved variable that's nowhere
in the natural empirical world of like
what is its probability of landing on
one side or the other. That's not a
feature of the world that can just be
measured with a stick, but it might be a
latent factor that we're very interested
in, like is this a fair coin?
So there's unobservables in the world
that are whether they're mechanistically
related to something that exists but we
just didn't measure or whether they are
something that that doesn't specifically
exist in any location. There's all kinds
of latent states in the world that we
want to infer. And big picture that
basically is what makes something
cognitive or computational phenotyping.
The second reason is to compare
alternative hypotheses.
So different model structures that
represent different explanations for
behavioral phenomena. So in the first
situation, we're conditioning upon a
structure of a model and then we're
going to run it back to see if
individuals or treatment groups differ
in some aspect of that model. Like we
have a latent model of suitability
uh and then we're going to see if two
birds differ in how they're treating
suitability. The second situation is
like we have a bird movement data set
and we have two different models that
might explain suitability and now we're
going to compare which of these models
of suitability is more parsimmonious or
explains the data better. So in this
empirical grounding sometimes we're just
going to have one model and we're going
to run it back to see how individuals
and groups differ. A second situation is
we're going to have a portfolio of
models and we're going to go from the
empirical data to ask which of these
empirical uh which one of the generative
model architectures have the most
empirical support.
Um 9.3 is kind of a mathematical aside
on variational applause.
This is a way to fit distributions with
a central tendency.
There's more detail we can go into, but
big picture, it's a incrementally
optimizable strategy for fitting a
central tendency to a distribution.
9.4 poor parametric empirical bay or
peeb sounds kind of poly salabic but it
accords with a pretty intuitive way that
people think about basian statistics
which is there's always this question of
well what about the prior or isn't there
an influence of the prior on the
posterior there is that's kind of the
whole point so how do you ever really
know that the posterior results which
are after data are not being unduly
enclosed by your priors. So there's
different strategies on this. One of
them is to start with multiple different
prior starting points. So we're going to
have that coin and then we're going to
start from a prior of a uniform prior
kind of flat across all the 0ero to one
and then we'll start with different
starting points for more opinionated
priors. And if all of those are
converging on the same value, then we
feel more grounded in saying that we're
getting a posterior that represents the
informationational signal of the data.
We're not just passing through our
priors. Another way to have an empirical
grounding for prior selection is
empirical base, which is you have some
data sets. So we have flipped the coin
100 times and it was 7030 heads to
tails. So in that situation, we can just
start our prior with 7030. So it's kind
of like the first phase is a frequentist
phase or just using a maximum likelihood
solution. You're just taking the doing
the classical frequentist thing, taking
the plain maximum likelihood
straightforward empirical results that
you have for the first part of your
experiment and then re-entering that
with uncertainty into a basian model.
So, let's just say you don't necessarily
know um what should the blood dilation
parameter be for this or that treatment
group in this fMRI experiment. It's like
it's not going to be something you can
just figure out pencil and paper or with
a computer, but you might be able to
grab a subset or a different fMRI
experiment and then say, okay, well, the
range that we ever observed for that
parameter was one to five. So let's just
set our parameter as 0.5 to 10 to go
beyond what has ever been empirically
observed and then we'll sharpen it from
there.
So that's a short section just
describing how and and this has gone
into a lot more detail in the SPM
textbook and and methods. This is
basically just saying if you're
concerned about prior influence on
posterior as as basians are then you can
do different strategies you can try
different priors different precisions on
priors or you can just start with
setting your prior based upon what's
empirically already found on a subset of
the data.
Section 9.5. This is kind of a lot like
chapter six. That's the kind of Jimmyi
Hendris if six were nine part of this
book, which is chapter six was the
recipe for creating that generative
model and going step by step in that
forward direction. That was the recipe
for building the music box to get to the
sol. Now we're going to work back and
say what are the steps if we have this
data set and we are trying to do
analysis on the data set in order to get
to a publication or something that looks
like that. So here are the steps and and
here's the SPM
package. It'll be kind of a um a
little bit of an exploration away from
the textbook, but we could look at SPM
if people want or perhaps better in a
separate group. So, first collect the
behavioral data.
There's a ton that could be said about
ethology and and behavioral data
analysis, but this is going to look like
what's the real-time data that you're
describing?
How' you how did those behaviors get
defined?
What are the parameters that you're
observing? You know, what's the
temperature? What time of day was it?
What did you define this behavior as?
How did you measure it? Okay. Step two
is chapter six. Here they say chapter 7
because they're talking about the
discrete time VP, but maybe they meant
chapter six actually. Um, more
generally, right, you do need to build
the generative model that's going to
receive
and and output the structure of the data
that you're looking for. That's where
the generative model that you write is
going to come up alongside and
recapitulate the empirical structure of
like the stimuli that you controlled in
your lab.
You want to have the the observations
incoming to the rodents.
The actions that you're studying the
output of the rodents, you want to be
the behaviors that you observe in the
lab.
That's the kind of closed loop.
Specify a likelihood function. You can
look back to chapter 2 with like the
likelihood of the apple or the frog
jumping.
Step four, specify the prior beliefs.
That was this earlier discussion. You
could start from a variety of prior
positions or you could do the parametric
empirical base
use some standard inference scheme like
variational applause. So that's why it
was brought up earlier in this chapter
to kind of go back from the observations
and then ask well what's the most likely
parameters of the underlying model that
would have given rise to those empirical
observations
and then do
ANOVA like statistics.
So analysis of variance, this is where
you start getting p values and things
like that for looking at how different
groups and within and among groups or
within and among treatments have
variability in those latent inferred
parameters. Because if you just wanted
to say
uh do an ANOVA on the descriptive
statistics, look at just primary
empirical variation within and between
groups in measurements.
You could do that with a purely
descriptive framework, purely
frequentist framework because you're not
inferring any latent variables. There's
nothing that isn't just being
empirically set from the measurement.
But if you want to start dealing with
features of the situation that aren't
directly measurable, like again the coin
tendency is not directly measurable. So
if you want to talk about comparing the
coins in terms of their propensity to
one side or the other, you're talking
about variables that aren't simply
observable. But if you just wanted to
flip a bunch of coins a thousand times
and then just say, well, which one came
up heads more? You don't even need to do
statistics.
So here's what those steps look like and
this is in reference to chapter 7. So we
already had this data set. Maybe the
previous grad student in this team a
setting gave us this data set.
The generative model Allah chapter 6 and
7 gets formed again just like figure 9.2
to kind of closing the loop. Other side
of the coin, other side of the handshake
from this rat. Chapter 7 was looking at
it from the rat's perspective. Now we're
looking at it from the laboratories
perspective in terms of what data we're
going to analyze.
priors and likelihoods come in to this
model inversion step which can be a
little tricky to get set up but there
are standard methods and there's some
examples in SPM and other toolkits but
then what you end up getting are
projecting from observations of data and
then basically the empirical data
the likelihood and the prior come
together like in this reactor or
crucible of the generative
and then it projects
onto this latent variable which could be
like um hunger level. So maybe we find
that as we we suspect that as a function
of time since eating the last food that
the the rodent is going to differ in its
decision- making and
um we could test the hypothesis whether
being um more hungry is going to lead to
it being more um risk-taking and just
going for the the gamble or whether it's
going to improve its its seriousness and
that's going to make it go to the
epistemic queue more. That would be like
kind of end level hypotheses that we
want to have empirical evidence for. And
we say, okay, we did five different
treatment groups. We had five different
intervals of of timing after last
eating.
And then we inferred this parameter.
And here's the mean and the variance of
each of those replicates plotted as a
bar chart. And then that's where we can
do an ANOVA. You can say these three,
you know, do or don't significantly
differ from these two. These two do do
or don't significantly differ from each
other.
And then that's kind of the result would
be like, you know, early phase this,
you know, but not, you know, or late
late phase hunger but not early phase
hunger increases exploratory behavior in
a rodent.
And that's kind of the paperlike
conclusion that gets yielded at the end
of all of the steps.
But the important feature was we're
talking about differences within and
among groups that are not simply a
descriptive feature of the world. So we
have to do this kind of latent or
abduced or inferred variable. And we
want that abduced variable not just to
be fantastical
but something that has a structurally
typed and interpretable basis where
there's modular prior and likelihood
specification.
So we can come to a empirically grounded
scientific conclusion by this stage.
9.6 goes into some settings where that
type of process has been followed.
Um
this is two different eye movement
examples. The left one is in a
continuous
setting
and the right one is in a discrete set.
9.7
goes a little bit into this kind of
territory of false inference, but of
course it's a real inference. It's just
not necessarily
of a ridical
conclusion.
This is sort of like there there's
there's a ton of of of harder and softer
discussion more on just the linguistics
and just what's a pathology, what's
normal, all those kinds of things all
the way on through the the real details
of parameterizing cognitive models. But
table 9.1 has a variety of these
different phenomena
and citations to explore how they're
dealt with.
This is a good um
pointer paragraph, but you know, why
does this matter? Why can't we just look
at the empirical data? Why can't we just
look look at people's behavior and just
classify them on on simple descriptives?
Like what if we have a model like this,
we could start to explore what scenarios
or what data sets would we want to
collect to determine like okay we're
seeing this kind of behavior
you know insert your favorite
phenomena. Is that due to the prior
beliefs
being a certain way?
Is that due to there being a inability
to update latent states? Is that due to
uh offkilter belief about how latent
states observe uh connect with
observables?
So those are the kinds of of
interpretability that you get with a
phase graph of cognitive modeling.
You could also just put a big neural
network or LLM transformer
and that could do a great job with
classification,
but then you might have low
interpretability.
And so that's the kind of funny thing is
then you need to do this whole second
layer of interpretability analysis to
look at like I vectors of activation in
the neural network to get back down to
what you hope might be a semantic or a
symbolic aspect of behavior.
the one approach isn't isn't uh better.
You'll see many papers arguably vastly
more that just take um
single or multimodal data set or gene
expression or neuro imaging and just do
machine learning or just we did a neural
network classifier to classify cancer
versus not cancer.
It's it's not a mechanistic or symbolic
account underlying cancer. It's just
data processing and clustering.
So that's where the main
contents of the book
get the reader.
Penn is going to revisit and extend on a
on a review footing
and and open up some some
ongoing
directions
and kind of leave for for a
consideration and discussion about
is active inference a unified theory of
sentient behavior.
But in terms of the
the delivery of the upskilling of this
book,
it's really the two through nine
chapters where chapter 1 and 10 are
those bigger picture review.
Chapter 2 and three got us to chapter 4
with generative models through the low
and high road. Chapter five reviewed the
mammal neuroscience
papers
using generative models in mamleian
neuroscience.
Chapter six was a recipe for building a
generative model. Chapter seven and
eight went into generative models in
more detail in the discrete and the
continuous time setting. Chapter nine
talks about running it back and going
from empirical data to parameters that
you can infer about your generative
model and then the kinds of papers you
can write with that.
Any any like random thoughts or ideas or
questions on not
Um, in chapter nine, I'm still kind of
intrigued or uh stuck on the
observations being related to the
experimentter
and um I think figure 91
Yeah.
>> So, let's just say that um
the generative model of of the the mouse
and the T-mas and there's going to be
like two different colors flashed of
light and it's going to have to make a
decision in the T-maze based upon two
different flashed colors of light. or
there's an observation for the rodent
that's underneath the bottom position of
the teammates like the epistemic que. So
there's stuff like the agent that we're
studying, the rodent in the lab or the
bird outside or the person in the clinic
or the LLM that we're studying in the
sandbox or whatever it is, there's
something that's going to be an inbound
data point for it, that flash of light.
But from our laboratory setting, we're
controlling the sequence of the flash of
lights.
So it's an action from
the lab,
but it's an observation from the
perspective of the agent who's
integrating it. And then analogously,
the action selection like expected free
energy, policy inference, all the stuff
we're talking about with action
selection results in a movement action.
But that movement action is an
observation for us recording its data.
So that kind of takes us back to the
markoff blanket where it's like the O
and the U are the the two are are the
two directions
on the blanket interface.
And so whether we think about that flash
of light coming from us as an action,
it is also going to the rodent as an
observation.
And then the action is getting emitted
from the rodent as an action, but it's
getting received by the observer as a
data point.
But it's just two different views
on the same interface.
and just very, you know, interesting
with a dash line here and a dash line
here.
So that's kind of like where the the
hyper priors kind of at some point you
just say, okay, it's just that's where
the hyper prior stop because you could
you okay, but how did we choose
which light sequence to flash? We can
look at that policy inference.
But just it the great part about basian
inference is it makes where makes what
your priors and what the structure of
your problem.
It makes it clear what you did and
didn't leave open as a degree of freedom
versus just like well here's the data we
collected. The data speak for
themselves.
Okay.
Pen is going to review and connect dots.
Here's possibly one of the contentious
and and discussionoriented
claims.
Does active inference provide a complete
solution to the adaptive problems that
sentient organisms have to solve?
So, a lot of ways to to take that,
right?
Is there any part of 10 that somebody
wants to go to or or a question that
they want to explore or should we just
also continue with this linearly?
Okay.
So, 10 two
they're going to summarize the earlier
chapters. Chapter 1, chapter 2,
chapter 3,
chapter 4,
chapter 5, chapter 6,
78, 9.
more words but similar to what I said
earlier
connecting the dots
here they introduce Daniel Dennit's
concept of the whole iguana
which was like
a thought experiment saying hey maybe
instead of going deeper into one
specific cognitive function or into
multiple specific cognitive functions
and then thinking that we're going to
figure out the lateral the lateral
connections later. How about start with
a complete cognitive modeling approach
for something like an iguana although I
will say that insect whole body and
brain modeling is way more advanced and
and neat as well.
again more discussible slashcontentious
claims for people who who who could take
pro and con and and and
differ in a variety of ways. One benefit
of active inference is that it offers a
first principle account of the ways in
which organisms solve their adaptive
problems.
Like
what is a first principle account? What
would be a first principles account of
how organisms solve their adaptive
problems?
Does that already exist? Could it exist?
Could there be multiple first principal
accounts?
Are we focused only on how organisms
solve adaptive problems? Is that kind of
the problem to solve?
The normative approach pursued in this
book assumes it is possible to start
from the principle of variational free
energy minimization
and derive implications about specific
cognitive processes. So this is what it
means to have a unifying cognitive
model. That's what the chapter, that's
what the book, arguably, that's what the
field is looking to deliver on is
instead of this portfolio of specialized
models with different architecture,
different notation, different ontology,
different software packages, different
research communities, etc., etc., etc.
for memory, anticipation, and all these
different cognitive phenomena.
Maybe perception, action selection,
attention, emotion regulation, etc.
could be addressable within a unified
approach to cognitive modeling.
They kind of walk through that how this
um
softly
cybernetic autopoetic
but ultimately just kind of organismal
realist perspective helps us integrate
cognitive phenomena. By by keeping in
mind that there's actually a creature
out there having to do stuff in a niche,
we are going to get to the point of
being able to consider how memory,
attention, planning, etc. come together.
It's kind of like the nothing in biology
makes sense except in light of evolution
question. This is kind of like saying
well nothing in cognitive is going to
make sense except in light of the
cognitive scenario
that is being discussed
that could be seen as taological
but it also is actually the the the
space where all these otherwise
fragmented phenomena make sense.
different ways that pre that that
previous taxonomies of cognitive
functions have have been applied. Th
those taxonomies may or may not
be aligned
with different levels of kind of Mars
analysis.
So there's just there's an explosion
yesterday and today and tomorrow of
cognitive ontologies
and so what the scope of coverage of
those and the the way they overlap and
everything
there's just a lot of ways to slice this
cake.
They're going to argue that having this
kind of a normative perspective, which
makes it sound like it's the socially
normative perspective, but but there's
other things that could be kind of
inserted in there, like adopting a
generic unified
system, scientifically based ontology
with useful educational materials and
implementable open source software
may also help in identifying formal
analogies studied in different domains.
Like if we want to talk about memory in
LLMs or if we want to talk about
anticipation or planning of groups of
cells or something,
are we just going to leave that as a
linguistic metaphor or simile and just
say that it's kind of it's useful for
communication, but it's not going to
help us actually move that field of
research forward? Or
could we go beyond just remarking on
similarity
and actually talk about some of the the
real isomorphisms
and even cross apply different models
from different systems.
So we get to understand and and
juxtapose and integrate a variety of
phenomena within a given system like
rodent. But then also by having a
unifying normative approach, we could
also unify across different systems.
And then it it sets up the possibility
of developing more specific process
theories that connect abstract symbolic
cognitive processes to
neuronal or cellular mechanisms. So we
could have
a um sensemaking or classifying agent.
It could be an incilico computer agent.
It could be a robot. It could be a
mouse. It could be a person. They could
all be solving or doing the same
cognitive problem.
And then we could connect that to
specific process mechanistic theories
like
being able to do generalization
could be mapped onto the columnar
architecture of the neoortex.
That's like the thousand brains idea.
10 four goes into prediction.
There's more in common than different
between predictive processing and active
inference. But there's also important
points of difference. If what is being
predicted includes not just what is
perceived in and in the niche in the
world, but also what is to be done and
then that prediction of action becomes
enacted.
That's basically active inference.
Um
there's a kind of you don't want to just
continue to revive straw people
arguments again and again and again, but
there is this inertial gestalt
that we're dealing with an influx of
information. We're processing and
sifting and fine-tuning the incoming
information to come to a clear picture
of all of this messy overload of data.
That's like an inbound processing model.
And the kind of different posture that
understanding predictive processing and
active inference puts you on is like oh
actually the information coming in just
visually for example it's sparse
variable resolution variable amounts of
color big blind spot etc. We're not
dealing with a overload of incoming
information and doing a sorting
exercise. We're generating an unrolling
visual model and it's getting just
lightly updated through incoming data
which is quite sparse.
That connects with this self-evidencing
like understanding the imperative
not to be to maximize reward on some
auxilary reward function but for for
things to have a firsteness of just
being what they are and then through
their activity seeking to become what
they are in this way that's both like
very tlogical and deflationary and
simple but also very esoteric
1041 goes more into predictive
processing. So Andy Clark and Yaka Powi
are some of the big authors in that area
and active imprints builds on that with
more formalism
the high road free energy principle and
software implementations. Whereas most
of the discussion about predictive
processing, it's either kind of
qualitative philosophical like about the
difference between that inbound versus
more generative concept of perception
um or it's
specifically in reference to like
specific neurosircuitry of the mammal
brain. So kind of already at the level
of a process theory
perception.
Kristen and others
often go back to Helmholds
um
uh and and the
perception as an unconscious infrance.
And then I always come back to um live
stream 43.0
where Maria
um
kind of took it back to like
much
that was a great presentation within
this. Zero.
So that that that helps just give this
it again is easy to fall into that
inbound processing feel and that is the
trick
basian brain pretty similar to um
predictive processing
in that it stays focused on the brain
whereas of course the scope of active
inference doesn't have to be brain
centric
action
earlier section brought up perception.
So it kind of the um passive predictive
processing passive basian brain just is
consistent with like the brain is like
this observer individual behind a
one-way mirror sense making and then is
that sense making more about processing
incoming information or is that about
having a rich world model that gets
fine-tuned with incoming data and then
whether you come from predictive
processing or basing brain or just go to
active imprints. You also are like,
okay, now that observer is going to be
doing stuff. They're going to pivot in
their chair. They're going to do is
cades. They're going to move their head.
They're going to flip pages in books.
There's been a lot of discussions about
how the kind of embodiment of primary
sensory
information becomes integrated with
skilled action
and more cognitive and symbolic
kind of higher order cognitive features.
have you go from just having joint
control
to spelling out messages in sign
language
sign language uh cybernetics
uh
they field there's a v variety of ways
that people have looked at the
perception action cycle like t this is
kind of a a standard industrial
engineering frame test operate test exit
there's also the UDA, observe, orient,
decide, act, and a variety of other ways
that people have cut that cognitive
cake. Kind of to the earlier point about
there being such a variety of cognitive
ontologies and just so many different
ways. And that's why it helps to to be
familiar with a bunch but be fluids in a
few.
Perception is signal processing and
sense making. Action selection is often
called control.
That doesn't mean total control. It
doesn't mean lock step. It just means
basically action re-entry into a
situation.
So sensemaking and control,
perception and action, joint
distribution, that's the whole iguana.
So instead of just having the iguana
locked into a apparatus and then study
its discrimination behavior
and then put it out in a different
experiment and study its choice behavior
as if it was getting perfect information
from the environment. The whole iguana
is let's model the perception cognition
action of an agent as a joint
distribution
and then that can be a basian joint
distribution and then we can do all
these different equations in software
um utility and and there's so many ways
that people have gone with economics
but utility as we kind of found from
equation 26
utility is the pragmatic only special
case of decision-m
complimentary to the novelty only
epistemic value. Whereas expected free
energy is a synthetic
scoring for policy selection that could
could be
zero 100 could be 100 could be 8020
could be 50/50.
But in economics those kinds of
discussions micro and macroeconomics
those are classic discussions
like are people maximizing reward or
they satisfying
basing decision theory
example of how like just searching in
quotations active inference you'll find
some literature but I mean there might
be a basian decision theory paper using
an evidence lower bound using a
variational free energy so by all means
active inference and under the free
energy principle they just might not use
those words so it's kind of about
reading between lines and um
not just having syntax flags because
there's relevant work that just uses a
different or or work that's not written
in English, of course,
which is why it's important to have a
core ontology that isn't just grounded
in in a connotation of a term.
reinforcement learning, tons of of
connections with active inference and
and machine learning, especially
nowadays.
Planning.
Planning is action selection, including
counterfactual futures.
You quickly get into all the kinds of
things that the chess algorithms were
getting into in the 1980s like
combinatoric explosion of policies and
highly conditional sequences of action,
stuff like that.
Behavior
general topic, right? as many. It just
behavior is what is is what things do.
That
makes me think about a a paper of of my
PhD adviser from
the plant behavior. Think about nowadays
just podcasts and discourse and just how
there's so much focus on things being on
on things behaving
and it's like those debates have are
long standing
just who gets to behave what's
computation what's cognition
all that
bounded rationality
a lot of topics here especially like the
kind of AI alignment and safety space
trivially
all implemented systems are going to be
boundedly rational and all systems are
going to have this sense in which like
if you account for what they are they're
as rational as they are that's like the
the what's optimal about optimal basian
inference how can we say something
pathological is optimal but that's the
whole part from chapter nine
veance emotion motivation
Some of these higher order psychological
constructs, some of them even
experienced
that that people spend a lot of effort
on on modeling.
Homeostasis, allostasis, interception.
Some more
foundational organismal capacities
that also can be modeled within this
whole iguana approach.
How how do we extend the
um simple first order cybernetics like a
homeostat
into what what some sometimes people
call second order cybernetics like a
learning homeostat and then you get into
like third order. But, you know, at that
point, it's just like are we trying to
to um
you know what what linguistic ontology
is just being extended out? What's the
real question that's being addressed
other than just pointing and and and
labeling natural phenomena?
more
phenomena
open directions. I guess this is where
we get to learn and explore. These are
definitely things you'll see in the
discord in in the discourse
in papers today.
multi-agent
social
interactions amongst uh humans or
amongst all AIs or augmented groups,
robotics.
Summary: Lord of the Rings, possible
illusion to the ring on the cover of the
book.
Um kind of a personal
like ending section of the book in terms
of just the style of the writing
and they
lay it out pretty clearly.
What what did they ask?
What did they respond with? What was
their evaluation? So, kind of a little
bit of a Hegelian triad with these three
sentences.
They hoped and in the textbook group we
hope to extend
the introduction to those who use these
methods conceptually and formally.
Also the kind of third cousin there is
the computational because the conceptual
is often taken to me qualitative
philosophical
and formal to mean
analytical mathematical
and then it's easy to feel and actually
even have high familiarity with
philosophical and mathematical
but still not to be able to even write a
script that does a simple thing. So the
computational is a really important
piece too.
And then there's this funny turn
where they they kind of are like
remember how everything we said about
action
now go on.
And then it might look exactly the same
or it might be different.
And then there's the appendences.
So pretty pretty long chapter. I mean,
you could draw you could draw lines
coming out of this, especially some of
these short like six paragraph sections.
You could expand on it a lot.
Oh yeah, the last minutes. Where does
that kind of take anyone of any thoughts
or questions on
This part about the important rights of
passage I kind of get and like
theoretical neurobiology like Kristen's
research group is called the theoretical
neurobiology group.
So in this part I kind of got the sense
of Par and Pizulo being his students
and them kind of sharing this milestone
in their own tradition of
modeling.
Thank you Benjamin. Yes, good book and
thought provoke.
And this part here is just
that that that tantalizing
overlap of obvious and arcane.
I mean, what could be more obvious in
every day
than every every look, every breath you
take? all of that.
But then it's like but then the
cognitive and active inference gets
transposed into this other space that's
like well no we would need to have some
we need to do something different to see
how it applies dayto-day
versus just grounding it in our
basic physiological action
and then using that to kind of be like
well
was there an implicit reward reward
oriented model? Like, did you believe
that you were moving your eyes or
choosing restaurants or deciding what to
do around the house because of reward?
Or was it just something that hadn't
been considered?
>> Yeah, Benjamin, go for it.
>> So, tell me if this makes any sense.
Yeah, earlier one of the clauses you
pointed out was a little potent like
controversial maybe was that active
inference provides like a complete model
of cognition or something like I mean it
was something more qualified than that
but similar but it seems like yeah
that's only sort of true because it's
only as complete as your
mo yeah only as complete as your like
sensors and like your ability to
actually like record the data and
information you're getting from your
environment. And so the there you know
the equate the model the you can model
the dynamics but it's not this active
inference doesn't does isn't complete
because it doesn't have a complete
description of exactly what to measure
how to record it how to merge new data
with and model your priors and it's not
fully complete unless the model designer
suggests you know comes up with those if
that makes like does that make any sense
that my argument is that it doesn't seem
that complete unless
>> there's a lot more description of exact
actly what you know to pay attention to
what and what how to model your prior
and merge new updates into your prior
>> exactly
>> it's like what I have in this building
is a complete solution to all your
travel needs and it's like oh it's a car
it's like no
it's just metal and it's like but that's
not a solution to what I needed
but that's the what that was the
solution to what you needed Michael
Hi, I just um I wanted to sort of a side
note but in terms of getting more detail
on the implementation and things like
that um
is uh Sanjie's book that's coming in
March do you think Daniel that that will
be um building building out that
framework a little bit more? Oh yeah,
he's he's a fantastic developer and that
book will have a huge number of
notebooks and scripts. The math is more
comprehensive and it's going to be
completely tied to open source code in a
much stronger way. We're going to pivot
our textbook group focus there.
>> Awesome. Yeah. Okay. Thank you all. Till
next time.